<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rushi Panchariya</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Rushi Panchariya</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 09:05:10 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Let's Begin</title><link>/posts/lets-begin/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 09:05:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/lets-begin/</guid><description>Begin This is the new beginning and also my second blog, which is also a non-technical blog (first blog). I have decided to start writing blogs so that I can share my thoughts and knowledge and improve my writing skills. I will be writing blogs about mostly technical stuff and sometimes non-technical stuff. In technical blogs, I will cover whatever research I have done, and while doing research, I will keep my notes in the Notes section.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="begin">Begin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the new beginning and also my second blog, which is also a non-technical blog (&lt;a href="https://rushipanchariya.medium.com/how-to-use-face-api-js-for-face-detection-in-video-or-image-using-angular-fca1e4bef797">first blog&lt;/a>). I have decided to start writing blogs so that I can share my thoughts and knowledge and improve my writing skills. I will be writing blogs about mostly technical stuff and sometimes non-technical stuff. In technical blogs, I will cover whatever research I have done, and while doing research, I will keep my notes in the &lt;a href="/notes/">Notes section&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plan-and-present">Plan and Present&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As of now, I don’t have a full plan for what I am going to write, which topics I will cover, or where it will go. But I remember a quote that says to &lt;code>go with the flow and be more concerned with the journey than the destination&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A good traveler has no fixed plans, and is not intent on arriving.&amp;rdquo; - Lao Tzu&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>To start with, I will be writing blogs about &lt;a href="https://go.dev/">Golang&lt;/a>, which I am currently obsessed with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As said, I am currently obsessed with Golang, like how it internally works and all. I will start with its basics, and as I go along with my research, I will dig down into how Golang works internally. I am more curious to do research on its internal workings and its concurrency. I will try to explain all the things in an easy way (I hope so 😬).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I go with blogs, I will create YouTube videos for the same on my channel. I have lots of project ideas that I will create as an example, and if it is an interesting idea or helpful, I will make it open-source, or you guys can start contributing your ideas to the project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From my contribution, I have remembered how I struggled with starting to contribute to open-source projects. So definitely, I will write a blog about how to get started with open source. Also,share my experience with it. As of now,I am contributing to &lt;a href="https://github.com/ory/cli-vscode-extension">vscode-extension&lt;/a> for &lt;a href="https://ory.sh">ORY&lt;/a> organization, which mostly provides solutions in the areas of authentication, authorization, access control, and zero-trust networking with their open-source projects. I will create a new tab where I can keep track of the ideas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So my plan will be, in short:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Research on the topic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add to &lt;a href="/notes/">Notes&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Write blog&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make YouTube Videos&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="let-go">Let Go&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let us begin this journey and learn as we go. The start may not be great, but you have to start to be great.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>If you are interested, I created a track 7 years ago called &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/rex_official/lets-go-rex">Let&amp;rsquo;s Go&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Go</title><link>/notes/go/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/notes/go/</guid><description>ABc adksajd
basdas dsadasdkas
BBC dsajdajskd</description><content>&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="abc">ABc&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>adksajd&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="basdas">basdas&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>dsadasdkas&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="bbc">BBC&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>dsajdajskd&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>OAuth2 and OpenID Connect</title><link>/notes/oauth2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/notes/oauth2/</guid><description>OAuth 2.0 OAuth 2.0 is an open authorization protocol, which enables application to access each other&amp;rsquo;s data. OAuth 2.0 does not share password data but instead uses authorization tokens to prove an identity between consumers and service providers. In simple term it uses authorization process to jump from one service to another without tapping in a new username and password. If you&amp;rsquo;re logged into Google and used those credntials for any app (Sign with Google), you&amp;rsquo;ve used OAuth.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="oauth-20">OAuth 2.0&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>OAuth 2.0 is an open authorization protocol, which enables application to access each other&amp;rsquo;s data. OAuth 2.0 does not share password data but instead uses authorization tokens to prove an identity between consumers and service providers. In simple term it uses authorization process to jump from one service to another without tapping in a new username and password. If you&amp;rsquo;re logged into Google and used those credntials for any app (Sign with Google), you&amp;rsquo;ve used OAuth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>OAuth2 is the industry-standard protocol that enables secure machine-to-machine communication and grants limited access to data and services on behalf of users. The specification also covers delegated access to client types such as browser-based, server-side web, native/mobile apps, and connected devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>OAuth was originally designed for applications to get access to API&amp;rsquo;s (All they need to ability to access the API). OAuth doesn&amp;rsquo;t communicate with user information. OpenID communicate with user information.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>About</title><link>/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/</guid><description>Hi there Hello, I am Rushi Panchariya. I&amp;rsquo;m Software Engineer with passion for Gaming 🎮, Coding 👨‍💻 and Music 🎧.
I&amp;rsquo;m always excited to work on new technologies and learn more about them. I am excited to work on a project that will benefit the community and assist them address their difficulties in whatever manner possible. When I&amp;rsquo;m working on a project, a concept, or a task, I&amp;rsquo;m always intrigued about the outcome.</description><content>&lt;h1 id="hi-there-hahahugoshortcode4s0hbhb">Hi there
&lt;img src="/img/pikachu-running.gif" class="left" style="width: 50px;" />
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Hello, I am Rushi Panchariya. I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;strong>Software Engineer&lt;/strong> with passion for Gaming 🎮, Coding 👨‍💻 and Music 🎧.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m always excited to work on new technologies and learn more about them. I am excited to work on a project that will benefit the community and assist them address their difficulties in whatever manner possible. When I&amp;rsquo;m working on a project, a concept, or a task, I&amp;rsquo;m always intrigued about the outcome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feel free to visit my &lt;a href="https://github.com/imrushi">GitHub&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, there you have it&amp;hellip; enjoy!&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/</guid><description>Shopey Collabortive Project
Quickly capture what’s on your mind and create your shopping list. Record voice memos while on the move and have them automatically transcribed. Shopey makes it easy to capture a list for yourself, and share it with friends and family. Developed using Flutter and Java, with Google Firebase utilized for the database, hosting, and Google functions. CLI VSCode Extension Open-Source Contributor
Played a key role in the early stages of an open‐source Visual Studio Code extension development, aimed at enabling seamless interaction with Ory projects and services.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="shopeyhttpsplaygooglecomstoreappsdetailsidcomd2r2shopey">&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.D2R2.shopey">Shopey&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Collabortive Project&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Quickly capture what’s on your mind and create your shopping list.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Record voice memos while on the move and have them automatically transcribed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shopey makes it easy to capture a list for yourself, and share it with friends and family.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Developed using Flutter and Java, with Google Firebase utilized for the database, hosting, and Google functions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="cli-vscode-extensionhttpsgithubcomvinckrcli-vscode-extension">&lt;a href="https://github.com/vinckr/cli-vscode-extension">CLI VSCode Extension&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Open-Source Contributor&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Played a key role in the early stages of an open‐source Visual Studio Code extension development, aimed at enabling seamless interaction with &lt;a href="https://github.com/ory">Ory&lt;/a> projects and services.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proposed and contributed to the concept of the extension, providing valuable input to the organization.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Currently involved in the development of 7 to 8 commands for the extension, with ongoing contributions to enhance its functionality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Collaborating with a team of developers to ensure compatibility, functionality, and an optimal user experience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Project is currently in progress, with no specific release date set at this stage.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="datreehttpsgithubcomdatreeiodatreepullsqis3apris3aclosedauthor3aimrushi">&lt;a href="https://github.com/datreeio/datree/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+author%3Aimrushi">Datree&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Open-Source Contributor&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Datree is Open‐Source tool to prevent Kubernetes Misconfiguration.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It automatically validates Kubernetes objects for rule violations, ensuring no misconfigurations reach production. It’s an E2E policy enforcement solution that can be used on the command line, admission webhook, or even as a kubectl plugin.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contributed two CLI commands: completion and Docs. The completion command enables auto‐completion of sub‐commands upon double‐
tab, while the Docs command opens the documentation website in the user’s default browser.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="pothole-detector-using-iothttpsgithubcomimrushipothole-detector">&lt;a href="https://github.com/imrushi/Pothole-detector">Pothole Detector Using IoT&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Collabortive Project&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This project utilizes an IoT device mounted on a moped, bike, or car to detect and identify potholes on the road.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The system locates the potholes and displays their locations on Maps.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The project was implemented using the ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) stack and Python.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Raspberry Pi monitoring was achieved using Elastic Metricbeat.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="geo-dndhttpsgithubcomimrushigeo-dnd">&lt;a href="https://github.com/imrushi/Geo-DnD">Geo DnD&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Collabortive Project&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This is an Android app built with Java.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The app allows users to set a radius for a circle and select a location from Google Maps. Additionally, they can choose a mobile mode, such as general, silent, dnd, and more.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Once the user enters the designated circle, the mode is automatically set accordingly. When the user is outside the set radius, the phone
switches to general mode.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>There are more projects which you can find on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/imrushi?tab=repositories">GitHub&lt;/a> 😊&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item></channel></rss>