<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blog on Rushi Panchariya</title><link>/tags/blog/</link><description>Recent content in blog on Rushi Panchariya</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 09:05:10 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Let's Begin</title><link>/posts/lets-begin/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 09:05:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/lets-begin/</guid><description>Begin This is the new beginning and also my second blog, which is also a non-technical blog (first blog). I have decided to start writing blogs so that I can share my thoughts and knowledge and improve my writing skills. I will be writing blogs about mostly technical stuff and sometimes non-technical stuff. In technical blogs, I will cover whatever research I have done, and while doing research, I will keep my notes in the Notes section.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="begin">Begin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the new beginning and also my second blog, which is also a non-technical blog (&lt;a href="https://rushipanchariya.medium.com/how-to-use-face-api-js-for-face-detection-in-video-or-image-using-angular-fca1e4bef797">first blog&lt;/a>). I have decided to start writing blogs so that I can share my thoughts and knowledge and improve my writing skills. I will be writing blogs about mostly technical stuff and sometimes non-technical stuff. In technical blogs, I will cover whatever research I have done, and while doing research, I will keep my notes in the &lt;a href="/notes/">Notes section&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plan-and-present">Plan and Present&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As of now, I don’t have a full plan for what I am going to write, which topics I will cover, or where it will go. But I remember a quote that says to &lt;code>go with the flow and be more concerned with the journey than the destination&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A good traveler has no fixed plans, and is not intent on arriving.&amp;rdquo; - Lao Tzu&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>To start with, I will be writing blogs about &lt;a href="https://go.dev/">Golang&lt;/a>, which I am currently obsessed with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As said, I am currently obsessed with Golang, like how it internally works and all. I will start with its basics, and as I go along with my research, I will dig down into how Golang works internally. I am more curious to do research on its internal workings and its concurrency. I will try to explain all the things in an easy way (I hope so 😬).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I go with blogs, I will create YouTube videos for the same on my channel. I have lots of project ideas that I will create as an example, and if it is an interesting idea or helpful, I will make it open-source, or you guys can start contributing your ideas to the project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From my contribution, I have remembered how I struggled with starting to contribute to open-source projects. So definitely, I will write a blog about how to get started with open source. Also,share my experience with it. As of now,I am contributing to &lt;a href="https://github.com/ory/cli-vscode-extension">vscode-extension&lt;/a> for &lt;a href="https://ory.sh">ORY&lt;/a> organization, which mostly provides solutions in the areas of authentication, authorization, access control, and zero-trust networking with their open-source projects. I will create a new tab where I can keep track of the ideas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So my plan will be, in short:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Research on the topic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add to &lt;a href="/notes/">Notes&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Write blog&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make YouTube Videos&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="let-go">Let Go&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let us begin this journey and learn as we go. The start may not be great, but you have to start to be great.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>If you are interested, I created a track 7 years ago called &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/rex_official/lets-go-rex">Let&amp;rsquo;s Go&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>